We are still in the Properties
of Petri Nets part of this lecture.
Overall, however, we are nearing the
end of the Petri net chapter.
In fact, we will not
be introducing any more properties.
But in this video I want to
discuss an example, which was at the beginning
of the Petri net chapter, and which I
promised that we will look at later as a
Petri
net.
That was the
so-called feeding philosophers.
At the beginning of this example I
had also mentioned some properties which one
would like to know and
investigate of such a dynamical system.
We have formalized some of them in
the meantime and can now apply them to
this
example.
There were questions about the progress or dead
ends in which a system can end up.
Or whether individual actions, which we modeled as
transitions in a Petri net, can always occur
at least once or can even
be executed any number of times.
There were questions about fairness, which in
the case of philosophers was whether two
philosophers together could
starve the third.
There were questions about causalities, whether certain
actions are mutually dependent (which can be
found again here
with the example).
And also the last introduced
notions about concurrency and conflicts can
be related
to this example.
Questions about bounds or
capacities, i.e. boundedness or 1-safety,
which were also discussed last week,
have less application specifically to this
example.
We will look at those
separately again in a different context.
But as a reminder,
let's start with this example.
So what was
it all about?
There were these three philosophers
sitting around a round table.
And, of course, this is not
a Petri net that you see here.
This is simply a sketch,
a representation of the situation.
There are these three
philosophers P1, P2, P3.
They sit around
a round table.
And always between two philosophers there is
a fork (English: Fork, therefore F1, F2,
F3).
And then the description of the situation
gave that the philosophers get hungry from time
to time (we will
call that H_i for "hungry").
And then they would like to eat (this
will be labeled here E1, E2, E3 for the
three
philosophers).
And for that they
need both adjacent forks.
That is, if philosopher 1 wants to
eat, he needs forks 3 and 1.
And the procedure is that a philosopher
who is hungry picks up both forks at
any time, first the right one and only
when the right one is in hand, then
also the left one if possible
(if the left fork is still there).
Then they eat
with both forks.
And afterwards the philosopher puts the two
forks back on the table at the
same time, so that then maybe someone
else could grab one of these two forks.
So that was the verbal description
of the problem, now enriched by these
labels (I don't think that showed up
on the previous slide for this example).
Now we can try to model
this in principle as a Petri net.
And for that, I'm going to use exactly the
labels that have already appeared here in the Petri
net.
And these will be exactly
the places in the Petri net.
The philosophers
themselves will not.
They will not appear in the Petri
net themselves, but they are essentially marked
by their being
hungry and eating.
How could this
Petri net look like?
I simply give this,
on the one hand.
On the other hand, I will now
explain how the philosophers find themselves here.
Immediately obviously one
cannot recognize them here.
So, there are the places H, W,
F each numbered with 1, 2, 3.
And the meaning for example
of the place H1 shall be:
Philosopher 1 is hungry
or is ready to eat.
It will be that in
principle philosophers are always hungry.
It will not be modeled extra
that they have to get hungry first.
The point is that at any
moment a philosopher could decide to want
to eat (that is, be ready to eat),
and then try to reach for the forks
(to be
able to eat).
Since we know that there is this moment
where a philosopher who has already grabbed one fork
has to wait for the other fork,
there are the additional places W1, W2, W3.
They didn't appear like
that in the description.
This would be the state after the
right fork has already been gripped and,
if necessary, the left fork must be waited
for because it is not on the table.
For this purpose, a token
will be used at W1 or
W2
or W3.
To express that the corresponding philosopher
is waiting for the left fork.
Which also means that he
has already grabbed the right fork.
If a fork is not grasped,
then it is on the table.
This would correspond to the situation as it is
here, where the forks are really still on the
table.
And for that, a respective token
will be used on F1, F2, F3.
So we'll see that here in
the three places, so to speak.
And then there will be tokens on the
E1, E2, E3 spots when the corresponding philosopher
is
eating.
So, we don't see
the philosophers explicitly here.
But, of course, we can
still find them in here.
And that is, philosopher 1, for example, would ultimately
be represented here by this part of the Petri
net.
So the three passages on being hungry, on
waiting, and on eating, which relate to philosopher
1, and ultimately this
transition before the waiting passage.
This is also a transition that belongs to
philosopher 1, because this is where philosopher 1 first
becomes active (namely, when he is
hungry and finds a suitable fork, his
right fork,
on the table).
For philosopher 1, F3
is the right fork.
This would start the
action for philosopher 1.
Basically, this is philosopher 1, and accordingly
philosopher 2 can be found here in
the Petri net,
and similarly philosopher 3.
Then there are
the two forks.
They're really separate
from the philosophers.
They're just there, and they're
also initially assigned a token.
And there's
this transition.
We could actually have those
count towards philosopher 1 as well.
That would be the transition where philosopher
1 is done eating and releases the
forks.
So we find the three philosophers
again, expressed by this set of places.
The initial situation is that the three forks
are on the table (that's what we see here),
and that all three philosophers
are in principle ready to eat.
So they would be ready to reach for
forks in order to be able to eat then.
How are all
the convolutions justified?
For example, we see here that in
fact this action, which would result in
philosopher 1 waiting for the left
fork, depends on philosopher 1 actually being
hungry before and having already
taken the right fork from F3.
This would justify why these
are exactly the preconditions for this
transition that leads to then
philosopher 1 waiting for this fork.
Then we
can look at:
What has to happen
for philosopher 1 to eat?
He must have grabbed
the right fork beforehand.
That is, this waiting condition must
have been taken by philosopher 1, and
then he must be able to grasp the
left fork (which is fork F1 for philosopher 1).
So if this and this condition
are met, then philosopher 1 can eat.
Then there would be a token here
for philosopher 1, and then philosopher 1, when
he's done eating, would be
able to fire this transition.
And that would cause philosopher 1 to
go back to the state where he's
ready to eat, so again waiting for
the next time where he would eat.
And of course both forks, the left fork
and the right fork, would have to be
returned by
philosopher 1.
That's why there are these
two exit arrows from the transition.
And for Philosopher 2 and Philosopher 3,
that's just symmetrically repeated in each case.
So the other parts in this section
do the same thing for philosopher 3.
So much for the
kind of modeling here.
Then we can look at a
run, looking for properties that we've
already
seen.
Do we
recognize concurrency?
recognize conflict?
Can we say
something about liveness?
Let's assume that philosopher 1 is
the one who becomes active first.
So, for example, philosopher
P1 would like to eat.
What would
that mean?
It would mean P1 has to see that
he gets the first fork in his hand.
Of course, ultimately, philosopher 2 and
philosopher 3 also want to eat.
But let's assume that philosopher 1 will be
activated first and will also be able to successfully
fire this transition, because at the moment there is
the fork on the table that he needs for this.
So the first activated transition could
be that and the first executed action
could be that
this transition will fire.
Namely based on
these two tokens.
Of course, analogously, and concurrently to that,
philosopher 2 could also become active here
or philosopher 3
could become active here.
So here now this, this and
this transition would be activated concurrently.
There is no conflict in
the Petri net at the moment.
At least not
between these three transitions.
That's the only way I can say that, we'll have to
look at the rest to see if there are conflicts of
any
other kind.
So then P1 has
now taken the right fork.
That's why this token here has also disappeared,
and it's also no longer recorded that philosopher
1 wants
to eat.
Because he is, so to speak,
in the process of getting the food.
At least to have already grabbed the right
fork, in order to possibly be able to grab
the left fork
afterwards and to eat.
Let's assume that neither philosopher 2 nor
philosopher 3 get in the way somehow, and
philosopher 1 can
continue to act.
Then, of course, he could now
fire this transition, which would ensure that
he also takes the
other fork (his left fork).
Because now this
transition would be activated.
It was
not before.
not activated.
Why
not?
Because there was
no token here.
That is, this is a case of causality
here, because in fact this transition has to
fire before this
transition can ever fire.
That would be
a necessary condition.
This transition would be
a necessary condition for this.
And we also find this
analogously in the other philosophers.
What we also have
now is a conflict situation.
In the step before,
that was not the case.
There the three transitions were actually activated
concurrently, and there were also no other
activated transitions than this one,
this one and this one.
There one can convince oneself that all other
transitions are not activated, because in each case at
least one precondition
place is not occupied.
But now after executing the first
transition and then activating these transitions, it
turns out that
there is a conflict.
There is another transition, which
is now also activated or still
activated, but now is in
conflict with another transition here, namely
this
transition.
This transition is also activated, because
it finds a token in both of
its
precondition places.
But it overlaps in its preconditions in
a conflictual way with the now here
also
activated transition.
For both this transition and this
marked transition would like to consume this
token.
And since there is only one token there,
they cannot do that simultaneously, in parallel, concurrently.
Both, so both this Transition and this
Transition are activated, but they are not activated
concurrently.
So they're in conflict, precisely with respect
to this fork 1, because that's the
left fork for philosopher 1 and
the right fork for philosopher 2.
Let's assume that of the
two conflicting transitions, only the
one assigned to
philosopher 1 fires.
Then this would ensure that
now the token is here.
P1 has now also taken
the left fork and can eat.
F1 is empty, because Fork 1, the left
fork of philosopher 1, is taken from the table.
And now this place is marked
here, where philosopher 1 is eating.
And after that, philosopher 1 could
or should put the forks back.
In parallel, philosopher 3 could have reached
for the fork here, while philosopher 2
could have done nothing at all
(because this place is not occupied here).
Now, for example, philosopher 1 would
fire the transition that ends his eating
process.
And this is to make sure that
here, here, and here lie tokens again.
And
indeed:
After putting back the forks F3 and F1 by
philosopher 1, we are back to the initial situation.
This worked well because only P1
was active and not somehow P2, P3
interfered.
What other properties
could we observe?
Perhaps, for example, if P1, P2, P3
had not been so cooperative and had not
simply let
P1 do it.
For example, are there
also possibilities of entrapment here?
We already know intuitively
that this is the case.
Because we had discussed at the beginning
that actually P1, P2, P3 could behave unfavorably,
and thus the system could ultimately
end up in a dead state.
How could
that happen?
For example, if at the beginning, when
here these three transitions were activated concurrently,
the philosophers also just
greedily execute each this transition.
So they reach
for their right fork.
These three concurrently activated transitions could
fire all three in any
order.
This is shown here
as happening in parallel.
In reality it happens in any
order that this, this and this transition
fire.
Then we would be in this situation, where just
now all three philosophers are waiting for their left
fork in each case, but will
never get the opportunity to actually
be able
to progress accordingly.
Now all of them have
taken their respective right fork.
And none of them has the slightest
chance to reach for the left fork.
But it will also never happen that
one of the three now releases his grabbed
right
fork.
For this, for example, P1
would have to fire this transition.
For this, this transition would
have to have fired before.
But it can't, because
there is no token here.
And it can't get there either,
because the same is true for P2.
P2 can put back the right fork
only after the left fork could be grabbed,
but it can't do this, because
this would require this token here, etc.
Then we have indeed
reached a deadlock here.
This also tells us that the
model is certainly not strongly alive.
One might
still ask:
Is it at
least weakly alive?
The answer would be yes, because we have
seen that P1 can fire through for all its
transitions.
And P2, P3
could as well.
So at least each transition
is possible to execute once.
Not in
every pass.
But from the initial marking every
transition is in principle also once executable
by suitable choices
of sequences and steps.
Boundedness is
also present here.
I didn't try all cases
(we didn't build a reachability graph
and didn't explore all situations),
but it's easy to think that
this model
is even 1-safe.
Because at the beginning there was at most one
token per place, there are also no arrows with
any weights > 1, so these
syntactic properties for 1-safety are already fulfilled.
And if you run the model, you
will also find that there is never more
than one token
on any place.
Thus the model is 1-safe
and of course also bounded.